Guide to Culinary Ephemera: Flour Products, Leavening Agents, and Baked Goods ams.0058
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
- Flour Products
  - Box 12
    - Pillsbury's cook book. 48 p., 1929 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Item [2] from the Pillsbury Laboratory promotes Pillsbury products. Includes history of Pillsbury Flour Mills Company, founded by Charles A. Pillsbury; factory and product packaging illustrations; table of time, weights, and measures; and index. Sample recipes: fried drop cakes, planked fish, beef pot roast, baked beans, and pumpkin pie.
    - New recipes for Pillsbury's cake flour. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1930s (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Pillsbury's cake flour. Includes introduction from Ida Bailey Allen and serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations. Sample recipes: fairy cake and Portsmouth orange cake. Form 1568.
    - Bake the no-knead way, Ann Pillsbury's amazing discovery. 64 p., 1945 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Pillsbury flour. Includes description and illustration of new Ann Pillsbury kitchen; no-knead bread recipes with illustrated methods and homemaker testimonials; serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations; index; and signed message from Ann Pillsbury on last page. Sample recipes: nut bread, raised muffins, sausage muffins, and Swedish tea ring. 2 copies.
    - Faster, easier yeast baking for you: new recipes developed by Pillsbury. [8] p., circa 1950s (Box 12, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Pillsbury flour. Includes serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations and yeast bread hints. Sample recipes: simple bread and easy do sweet dough.
    - Kate Smith chooses her 55 favorite Ann Pillsbury cake recipes. 1st ed. 64 p., 1952 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Pillsbury Sno Sheen cake flour and other baking products. Includes list of products; cake making hints and method illustrations; serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations; Pillsbury extra-value coupon plan for premiums; and index. Cover includes illustration of Kate Smith and promotes her television program. Sample recipes: angel food cake, coconut chocolate cake, and cooked frostings.
    - Goin' nuts cookbook: nut cookery in over 120 delicious recipes. 96 p., 1975 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Pillsbury and Fisher Nut Company products. Includes cookery hints; nut information; serving suggestion, nut, and product packaging illustrations; 7 cent off coupon; and index. Sample recipes: poteca, peanut glazed rolls, beef casserole orientale, cashew baked fish steaks, and pecan cornbread turkey stuffing.
    - Working people's cookbook: the practical answer to "What's for dinner" in less than an hour. 95 p., 1978 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes Pillsbury products. Includes list of staples, quick cooking tips, substitutions, quick recipes, recipes for freezing, microwave hints, serving suggestion illustrations, and index. Sample recipes: make-ahead hamburger mix, creamy chicken crepe filling, potato corn chowder, savory flat bread, dress ups for tender steak, and no bake peanut butter cookies. Marked: F 06827.
    - Try these winning bake-off recipes: [folded brochure]., 1990 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Pillsbury and Green Giant products. Includes 1990 Bake-off winners and nutrition information by recipe. Sample recipes: blueberry poppy seed brunch cake and fudge crostata with raspberry sauce.
    - Freshest ideas from Pillsbury. [12] p., 1990 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Pillsbury products. Notes doughboy is 25 years old, dough products now cholesterol free, and microwave pans are reusable to reduce waste. Includes offer for Doughboy branded items and store coupons; origin of "XXXX" mark on flour; and serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations. Sample recipes: golden harvest squares and corn dog twists.
    - Freshest ideas from Pillsbury. [8] p., 1991 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Pillsbury products. Includes Poppin' Fresh Doughboy, children's page, and Poppin' Fresh presents and recipe cards with order form. Sample recipes: yummy bunny cake and orange mousse pie.
    - Six easy ways to celebrate the season: [folded brochure]., 1992 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes Pillsbury refrigerated cookie dough and Frosting Supreme. Includes serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations. Marked: 077-92-001A.
    - Pioneer recipes. 28 p., circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Pioneer Flour products. Includes serving suggestion, product packaging, and factory illustrations; list of products; baking hints; and measurements. Sample recipes: snickerdoodles, 100% whole wheat bread, sweet dough foundation, and orange date loaf cake.
    - Home baked treats with Purity Flour. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes Purity Flour. Includes serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations, baking hints, and coupons for New Purity cook book for $1.00 each. Sample recipes: sweet dough for tea rolls and ice box cookies.
    - Occident quick bread recipes (soft dough). 14 p., circa 1920s (Box 12, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes Occident Flour. Includes baking hints, measurements, score card for judging, and white sauce hints. Sample recipes: basic recipe for biscuit dough, raisin rolls, and steamed brown bread. Marked D 12.
    - Occident quick bread recipes (thick, medium, and pour batters). 10 p., circa 1920s (Box 12, Folder 16)
      Item [16] promotes Occident Flour. Includes baking hints, measurements, and score card for judging. Sample recipes: popovers, date cornmeal muffins, and French pancakes. 2 copies. Marked: D 15.
    - Occident cake recipes. 16 p., circa 1920s (Box 12, Folder 17)
      Item [17] promotes Occident Flour. Includes baking hints, measurements, and score card for judging. Sample recipes: variations of plain butter cake, devils food cake (sour cream), apple sauce cake, and pork and fruit cake. Marked: D 10.
    - Occident dessert recipes. 7 p., circa 1920s (Box 12, Folder 18)
      Item [18] promotes Occident Flour. Sample recipes: strawberry batter pudding, blitz torte, and French ice cream. Marked: D 14.
    - Occident yeast bread recipes. 14 p., circa 1920s (Box 12, Folder 19)
      Item [19] promotes Occident Flour. Includes baking hints with methods illustration. Sample recipes: raisin bread, hot cross buns, and California rolls. Marked: D 7.
    - Occident whole wheat bread recipes. 6 p., circa 1920s (Box 12, Folder 20)
      Item [20] promotes Occident Flour. Sample recipes: whole wheat bread and whole wheat bread pudding. Marked: D 13.
    - Occident sandwich recipes. 8 p., circa 1920s (Box 12, Folder 21)
      Item [21] promotes Occident Flour. Includes sandwich making hints and filling recipes. Sample recipes: vegetable club sandwich, peanut butter and pickle sandwiches, and mint cucumber sandwiches. Marked: D 8.
    - Occident pastry recipes. 10 p., circa 1920s (Box 12, Folder 22)
      Item [22] promotes Occident Flour. Includes pastry making hints. Sample recipes: rhubarb pie, chocolate cream pie, and rich puff paste. Marked: D 11.
    - Amazing new Softasilk method: [brochure]., circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 23)
      Item [23] promotes Softasilk cake flour. Includes illustration of Betty Crocker endorsing recipes, illustrated Softasilk method for better cakes, and high altitude adjustments. Recipes suggest baking powder such as Clabber Girl, Davis, Calumet, etc., with asterisk to phosphate type, such as Rumford, Dr. Price's, etc., or tartrate type, such as Royal, etc. Sample recipes: marble cake and brown sugar cake.
    - South Dakota wheat: [leaflet]., circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 24)
      Item [24] promotes South Dakota wheat. Sample recipes: Dakotaland sourdough starter, homesteader bread, and thousand mile biscuits.
    - How to bake by the ration book: Swans Down wartime recipes. 23 p., 1943 (Box 12, Folder 25)
      Item [25] promotes Swans Down cake flour and Calumet baking powder. Includes wartime recipes with sugar and shortening substitutes; baking hints; and serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations. Sample recipes: honey spice cake, favorite molasses cake, and low-shortening muffins. Marked: 7079.
    - Swans Down mix-easy cakes: [folded brochure]., 1945 (Box 12, Folder 26)
      Item [26] promotes Swans Down cake flour. Includes illustrated "easy-mix" method, electric mixer instructions, and product packaging illustration. Sample recipes: "mix-easy" ribbon cake and fudge nut cake.
    - Man-dasslin beauties, coconut dream cakes: [folded brochure]., 1948 (Box 12, Folder 27)
      Item [27] promotes Swans Down cake flour and Baker's coconut. Includes serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations. Sample recipes: ambrosia cake, tropical spice cake, and coconut mist cake. Marked: 9154-15.
    - McNess' products: the choice of Hollywood stars: [folded brochure]., circa 1933 (Box 12, Folder 28)
      Item [28] promotes McNess Champion flavoring extracts, baking powder, cocoa, cosmetics, and other products. Includes illustrations and testimonials from Hedda Hopper and other Hollywood stars, with biographical information on each. Notes stars were not paid.
  - Box 13
    Walker, P.O.
    Robson, Barbara Reid.
    Sands, Frank.
    Sands, Brinna B.
    Igleheart Brothers, Inc.
    Sands, Taylor & Wood Co.
    Valley City Milling Co.
    - [Gold Medal Flour recipes: recipe cards]., circa 1900s (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promoting Gold Medal flour consists of 7 recipes cards including illustration of Gold Medal logo.
    - The Gold Medal sandwich book. 35 p., circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes Gold Medal flour. Includes history of sandwich, hints and illustrations of sandwich making, elaborate serving suggestions, and index. Sample recipes: sandwich cheese loaf and date, nut, and cheese sandwich.
    - Foods men hurry home for / by Betty Crocker: [folded brochure]., 1936 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Gold Medal flour. Includes Betty Crocker and product packaging illustrations and coupon for free Wm. Rogers & Son silverware. Sample recipes: Great Lakes deep dish blueberry pie and squash rolls.
    - Give holiday hilarity a boost with "Gingies": [folded brochure]., circa 1936 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Gold Medal flour. Includes recipe for "Gingies", i.e., gingerbread boys; Betty Crocker and serving suggestion illustrations; and offer for free bread recipes. Series no. 3; 1. 2 copies.
    - Betty Crocker calico quilt cake: [folded brochure]., circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Gold Medal flour. Includes Betty Crocker, product packaging, and serving suggestion illustrations and offer for free bread recipes. Series 1; 1. Sample recipes: filled cookies, gold cake, and French strawberry pie.
    - First prize $5,000.00 for naming this cake: [folded brochure]., 1938 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Gold Medal flour. Includes contest rules, entry forms, and recipe for cake to be named; product packaging and serving suggestion illustrations; and coupon for medality silverware from Oneida community silversmiths. Notes flour is phosphated for consistency. Series 6; 1.
    - Betty Crocker urges you to try her sponge drop tea cakes: [folded brochure]., circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Gold Medal flour. Includes Betty Crocker and serving suggestion illustrations and coupon for medality silverware from Oneida community silversmiths. Phosphated. Series 4; 1. Sample recipes: ham shortcake and sponge drops.
    - Betty Crocker buttercup cake: [folded brochure]., 1942 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes Gold Medal flour. Includes serving suggestion illustrations and coupons for medality silverware from Oneida community silversmiths and Betty Crocker cookbook. Series 11; 2.
    - Your share: how to prepare appetizing, healthful meals with foods available today / Betty Crocker. 48 p., 1943 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      Item [9] was published by General Foods to provide information for economic and nutritious food preparation during wartime rationing. Includes foreword from Betty Crocker on women's roles as soldiers, in home defense, and making do with less; methods, recipes, and menus to extend rationed foods; nutrition information; advertisement for Softasilk cake-making methods; sample social events for wartime; product packaging illustrations; and index, Some sections use include poems and military language. Sample recipes: pinwheel meat roll, mock Indian pudding, war-time cake, service cake, and plentiful pot pie. Some loose pages.
    - Military Christmas cookies: [folded brochure]., circa 1943 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Gold Medal flour for wartime holiday baking. Includes offer for Betty Crocker cook book of "all-purpose" baking for 25 cents. Sample recipes: turkey cream pie and military Christmas cookies.
    - Fruit filled cream puffs: [folded brochure]., circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      Item [11] OUT FOR EXHIBIT.
    - French apple pie: [folded brochure]., circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes Gold Medal flour. Includes serving suggestion illustrations; testimonial with illustration from Barbara Reid Robson, home economics consultant; and offer for Betty Crocker party favors. Notes flour is now "enriched in the interests of public health in connection with the National Defense Program." Series 7; 1. Sample recipes: French apple pie and graham gems. 2 copies.
    - $1,000.00 in prizes for naming it: [folded brochure]., 1940 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Gold Medal flour. Includes rules and entry form for cake-naming contest and serving suggestion illustrations. Series 4; 1. Sample recipes: corn griddle cakes, gingies, and banana cream pie.
    - [Betty Crocker recipes with General Mills products: 6 folded brochures]., circa 1950s (Box 13, Folder 14)
      Item [14] consists of 4 items promoting Gold Medal flour. Includes Betty Crocker, serving suggestion, and product packaging illustrations, coupons, and cookbook offers. Sample recipes: Swedish tea ring and coconut washboards.
    - Choice recipes: Igleheart's perfect biscuit mix: [folded brochure]., circa 1920s (Box 13, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes Igleheart's biscuit mix. Sample recipe: golden waffles.
    - King Arthur Flour WinterBake: [folded brochure]., 1990 (Box 13, Folder 16)
      Item [16] promotes King Arthur flour. Includes adult and children baking competition, Winterbake, with grand prize of trip for2 to England; offer of 200th anniversary cookbook for $20 signed by Frank and Brinna Sands, owners; and product packaging illustrations.
    - The baking sheet. Vol. 9, no. 5, summer, 1998. 28 p. (Box 13, Folder 17)
      Item [17] promotes King Arthur flour and baking. Includes article on Iceland and its cuisine with recipe for Pönnukökurjökull; recipes shared by readers; and index.
    - The baking sheet. Vol. 9, no. 6, autumn, 1998. 28 p. (Box 13, Folder 18)
      Item [18] promotes King Arthur flour and baking. Includes article on artisan break making in the U.S.; recipes shared by readers; and index.
    - The baking sheet. Vol. 10, no. 1, holiday, 1998. 28 p. (Box 13, Folder 19)
      Item [19] promotes King Arthur flour and baking. Includes holiday recipes, e.g., chocolate truffles, gingerbread house, and Gwen's challah; recipes shared by readers; and index.
    - The baking sheet. Vol. 10, no. 3, early spring, 1999. (Box 13, Folder 20)
      Item [20] promotes King Arthur flour and baking. Includes article on 1999 Coupe du Mode de la Boulangerie; recipes shared by readers; and index.
    - Walker's method of easy bread making and practical money saving hints on cooking / by P.O. Walker. 31 p., 1916 (Box 13, Folder 21)
      Item [21] promotes Lily White Flour. Includes illustration of P.O. Walker, baking specialist, illustrated methods for making Parker House rolls, and product packaging illustration on back cover.
  - Box 14
    Hines, Duncan, 1880-1959.
    Allen's.
    H-O Company.
    Quaker Oats Company.
    Procter & Gamble Company.
    Homestead Mills.
    Omar Mills Inc.
    Randolph Mills, Inc.
    Reliable Flour Company.
    A.E. Staley Manufacturing Company.
    - Recipes to be used with Allen's fresh ground products: [brochure]., circa 1920s (Box 14, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Allen's fresh ground products: R.I. Meal, yellow corn meal, rye meal, and whole wheat flour. Sample recipes: Indian pudding and rye drop cakes.
    - The Presto family. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1910s (Box 14, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes Presto flour. Includes poem describing party with baked goods made successfully with Presto, cartoons illustrating poem, product packaging illustration, and advertisement for Hornby's Oatmeal. No recipes. Marked: P. M. 4001.
    - America's most famous recipe. 11 p., 1927 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes Aunt Jemima Pancake Flour and Prepared Buckwheat Flour. Includes the legend of Aunt Jemima; cover illustration of Aunt Jemima; product packaging and recipe illustrations; and advertisement for Aunt Jemima rag dolls. Sample recipes: green corn pancakes and sweet potato waffles.
    - A recipe no other mammy cook could equal. 15 p., 1930 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Aunt Jemima Pancake Flour and Prepared Buckwheat Flour. Includes legend of Aunt Jemima; illustrations of Aunt Jemima (on cover), product packaging and recipes; and information on and illustration of Mother's Coupons found in each package. Sample recipes: green corn pancakes and sweet potato waffles.
    - 12 magic menus from Aunt Jemima's album of secret recipes: [brochure]., circa 1910s (Box 14, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Aunt Jemima Pancake Flour and Prepared Buckwheat Flour. Includes 9 breakfast and 3 supper menus; hints for making pancakes and waffles; and product packaging and serving suggestion illustrations.
    - Aunt Jemima new temptilatin' recipes. 18 p., circa 1949 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Aunt Jemima's Ready-Mix for Pancakes and Ready-Mix for Buckwheats. Includes legend of Aunt Jemima, illustrations of Aunt Jemima and serving suggestions, menus, and nutrition information for pancakes with reference to Government's Recommended Dietary Allowances. Sample recipes: coffee cake and sausage patties. Marked: AJBR-1-49.
    - Bakery mixes: [folded brochure]., circa 1950s (Box 14, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Dawn baking mixes, GM Bisquick, and Red Star Active Dry Yeast. Includes directions for using active yeast; table of comparative weights and measurements for compressed, active dry, and instant active dry yeast; and cover illustration of baked goods. Sample recipes: Dawn cake donut mix, Dawn buttermilk biscuit mix, and GM pie crust mix.
    - How to take a trick a day with Bisquick as told to Betty Crocker. 41 p., 1935 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes Bisquick. Includes menus and recipes for various occasions (smart bridge luncheons, campfire meals, trousseau tea, etc.) "as told to Betty Crocker by screen stars, society stars, home stars, and star home making editors"; pictures of contributors, elaborate table settings, serving suggestions, and product packaging; testimonials; free recipe coupon glued in; and index. Sample recipes: gingerbread, caramel dumplings, and turkey ring. Marked: A595.
    - Bisquick holiday bakeshop. [7] p., 1977 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Bisquick. Includes introduction by Betty Crocker and illustrations of displays of baked goods and product packaging. Possibly distributed with McCalls magazine. Sample recipes: Christmas coffee ring, orange nut bread, and apricot kolaches. Marked: McCalls; A32330.
    - The Bisquick "no time to cook" recipe book featuring impossible pies. [7] p., 1982 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Bisquick. Includes introduction by Betty Crocker, colored photographs of recipes and product packaging, and offer to join the Bisquick recipe club. Possibly distributed with Family Circle magazine. Sample recipes: impossible taco pie and impossible brunch pie. Marked: Family Circle; A 38346.
    - "Chocolate is a man's favorite frosting" says Duncan Hines: [brochure]., circa 1950s (Box 14, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Duncan Hines cake mixes. Includes picture of Duncan Hines, one recipe for cake filling and two for cake frostings. Sample recipes: pineapple filling and creamy golden frosting. Marked: W-1.
    - Favorite recipes No. 2. 96 p., undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
      Item [12], issue no. 2 of Favorite recipes magazine with distinctive title on cover: Quick & easy baking with Duncan Hines cake mixes. Promotes Duncan Hines cake mixes. Includes glossy color illustrations of recipes, success tips for cakes with illustrations, removable insert coupon for discount subscriptions to magazine, and index. Sample recipes: dump cake, Thanksgiving cranberry cobbler, and carrot muffins. Marked: WPS 37500.
    - Homestead Mills: recipes from the wood. 39 p., circa 1987 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      Item [13], "a collection of recipes from Northern Minnesota bakers and sportsmen," promotes Homestead Mills products (hot cereals, pancake mixes, flours, wild rice, chili mix, and coffee). Typed manuscript with pages stitched along fold. Includes product illustrations, cover illustrations of Minnesota scenes, list of new products from Homestead Mills, order form for mail order price list, and index. Some recipes are attributed, with name and city of contributor. Sample recipes: Indian fry bread, Aunt Kel's Norwegian flatbrod, and trappers pancakes.
    - Blue ribbon recipe book. 30 p., 1938 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes Omar Wonder Flour. All recipes, blue ribbon winners at a state or county fair, tested in Omar's model food kitchen and by jury of home makers in their own homes. Includes pictures of Omar model kitchen and 31 homemakers with names and addresses, color pictures of recipes, list of 8 wonder features of Omar Wonder Flour, and index. Recipes annotated with changes needed for high altitudes. Sample recipes: apple pie, French coffee cake, and rice muffins. Loose leaflet insert promoting Kroger's Country Club Flour. Loose one-page handwritten insert with 2 recipes.
    - Recipes using Dainty Biscuit Flour and Randolph Corn Meal. 15 p., circa 1940s (Box 14, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes Dainty Biscuit Flour and Randolph Corn Meal. Includes convenience methods for biscuits (frozen biscuit, refrigerator dough, and partially baked biscuit methods). Sample recipes: mayonnaise muffins, blue cheese flakes, and lemon chess pie.
    - Biscuits and cakes: the "reliable" method. 62 p., 1911 (Box 14, Folder 16)
      Item [16] promotes Reliable Prepared Flour, Corn-Cake, and Graham. Includes tips for making shortcake and cake, recipes for when "eggs are up in price," measuring hints and table of measures, advertisement for Martson's Restaurant, and index. Sample recipes: twin mountain muffins, banana shortcake, and lily cake.
    - Reliable Flour Company: prepared flours: [broadside]., circa 1920s (Box 14, Folder 17)
      Item [17] promotes Reliable products. Includes letter promoting the products, product and serving suggestion illustrations, and order form. No recipes.
    - The Stoy cook book. 47 p., 1944 (Box 14, Folder 18)
      Item [18] promotes Stoy soy flour. Includes serving suggestion and product packaging illustrations, page promoting nutritional benefits of Stoy, and page on using Stoy in place of regular flour with associated table of proportions (inside back cover). Sample recipes: Stoy muffins, Stoy butterscotch sauce, and Stoy meat loaf.
  - Box 15
    Daniels, Frank.
    Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1850-1919.
    Gans, Nellie Duling.
    Hamel, P. J.
    Commercial Milling Co.